window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Operating_System - System_Call — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "System_Call — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following code snippet using the fork() and wait() system calls.\nAssume that the code compiles and runs correctly, and that the system calls run\nsuccessfully without any errors.<pre><code>\nint x = 3;\nwhile(x &gt; 0) {\nfork();\nprintf(\"hello\");\nwait(NULL);\nx--;\n}</code></pre>\nThe total number of times the printf statement is executed is ___ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "14",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422795/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Which one or more of the following options guarantee that a computer system will\ntransition from user mode to kernel mode? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Function Call</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>malloc Call</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Page Fault</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>System Call</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Page Fault</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>System Call</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399299/gate-cse-2023-question-13#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following standard C library functions will always invoke a system call when executed from a single-threaded process in a UNIX/Linux operating system? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>exit</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>malloc</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>sleep</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>strlen</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>exit</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>sleep</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357438/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-14#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The following C program is executed on a Unix / Linux system:<pre><code>#include &lt; unistd.h &gt;\n  int main() {\n    int i;\n    for (i = 0; i &lt; 10; i++)\n      if (i % 2 == 0) fork();\n    return 0;\n  }</code></pre>\nThe total number of child process created is __________ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "31",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302831/gate2019-cs-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The difference between a named pipe and a regular file in Unix is that <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Unlike a regular file, named pipe is a special file</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The data in a pipe is transient, unlike the content of a regular file</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Pipes forbid random accessing, while regular files do allow this.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>All of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>All of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213575/isro2018-13\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The following C program:<br><pre><code> {\n    fork(); fork(); printf(\"yes\");\n    \n}</code></pre>If we execute this core segment, how many times the string yes will be printed? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only once</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2 times</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>4 times</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8 times</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>4 times</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213584/isro2018-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>The Linux command<br><pre><code> mknod myfifo b 4 16</code></pre> <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>will create a character device if user is root</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>will create a named pipe FIFO if user is root</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>will create a block device if user is root</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>will create a block device if user is root</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128774/isro2017-72\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Wha is the output of the following program?<br><pre><code> main()\n{\n    int a = 10;\n    if(fork()) == 0))\n        a++;\n    printf(\"%d\\n\",a);  \n}</code></pre><br> <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10 and 11</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>11 and 11</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>10 and 11</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128699/isro2017-51\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following program.<br><pre><code> main()\n{\n    fork();\n    fork();\n    fork();\n}</code></pre>How many new processes will be created? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2015)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/51698/isro2015-37\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Identify the correct order in which a server process must invoke the function calls accept, bind, listen, and recv according to UNIx socket API. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>listen, accept, bind, recv</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>bind, listen, accept, recv</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>bind, accept, listen, recv</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>accept, listen, bind, recv</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>bind, listen, accept, recv</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8108/gate2015-2-23#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A process executes the code <br>\nfork(); <br>\nfork(); <br>\nfork(); <br>\nThe total number of child processes created is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/40/gate2012-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following UNIX command allows scheduling a program to be executed at the specifies time? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>cron</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>nice</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>date and time</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>schedule</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>cron</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52822/isro2011-57\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Fork is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the creation of a new job</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the dispatching of a task</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>increasing the priority of a task</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>the creation of a new process</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>the creation of a new process</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50002/isro2008-63\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the execution of the following commands in a shell on a Linux operating system.<br><br>\nbash$ cat alpha<br>\nMathematics<br>\nbash$ In alpha beta<br>\nbash$ rm alpha<br>\nbash$ cat &gt;&gt; beta &lt;&lt; SAME<br>\nInformation Technology<br>\nSAME<br>\nbash$ cat beta<br><br>\nThe output of the last command will be: <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Mathematics Information Technology SAME</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Mathematics Information Technology</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Information Technology</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Information Technology SAME</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Information Technology SAME</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "NOTE: This question is out of Syllabus Now.<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3274/gate2008-it-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>A process executes the following code<pre><code>for (i = 0; i &lt; n; i + +) fork( );</code></pre>The total number of child processes created is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{n+1}-1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-1\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/489/gate2008-66#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
